# MATTHEW I. SWINDALL, PH.D.

matthew.swindall@outlook.com

in linkedin.com/in/matthew-swindall

https://github.com/mis2n

 → +1 615-569-3904
 https://mis2n.github.io
 Nashville, TN USA

### **Professional Profile**

Accomplished computational scientist with AI and machine learning research experience and a background in physics and astronomy. My research focuses on interdisciplinary applications of AI methodologies including object detection, Handwritten Text Recognition (HTR/OCR), Natural Language Processing (NLP), and statistical analysis. I am the creator of the AL-PUB Dataset, a large-scale, crowdsourced image dataset containing Greek characters on ancient papyri for computer vision tasks. Additional interests include robotics, quantum computing, HPC, blockchain and smart contracts, and graph databases.

## **Education**

Ph.D. Computational Science	Middle Tennessee State University	2024
M.S. Computer Science	Middle Tennessee State University	2024
B.S. Physics	Middle Tennessee State University	2016
A.S. Physics	Columbia State Community College	2016

#### **Skills**

AI/ML Concepts	Deep Learning, Neural Networks, Convolutional Neural Networks, Recurrent Neural Networks, Generative Adversarial Networks, Reinforcement Learning, Transfer Learning, Autoencoders, Transformers	
AI/ML Libraries	TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, SciKitLearn, spaCy, BERTopic, NLTKs	
Computer Science	Unix/Linux, Parallel processing, cluster computing (SLURM), Ethereum Blockchain & Smart Contracts, Neo4j (Graph Database)	
<b>Coding Languages</b>	Python, C/C++, R, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, SQL, Solidity, Cypher	
Python Libraries	NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, Matplotlib, OpenCV	
Mathematics	Linear Algebra, Calculus, Differential Equations, Probability, Statistics	
Physical Sciences	Physics, Astronomy, Chemistry, Engineering, Electronics	
Additional Technical	Iot, Raspberry Pi, Arduino, Robotics, 3D Printing, CAD, CNC	
Soft Skills	Research, Publications, Public Speaking, Teaching, Science Outreach, Technical Writing, Project Management, Team Leadership	

## **Internships & Honors**

- La Serena School for Data Science, Class of 2021 NFS & CMM/UChile funded Data Science for Astronomy Program in partnership with NOIRLab/AURA-O
- MTeach Summer Internship, 2016 STEM teaching internship in partnership with the Discovery Center at Murfree Spring.

## Refereed conference proceedings

- Graham West, Matthew I. Swindall, James H. Brusuelas, Francesca Maltomini, Marius Gerhardt, Marzia D'Angelo, John F. Wallin. A deep learning pipeline for the palaeographical dating of ancient Greek papyrus fragments. in the Machine Learning for Ancient Languages (ML4AL) Workshop at the 62nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL). 2024
- Swindall, M. I., Upadhyay, K., Brusuelas, J. H., West, G., & Wallin, J. F. (2024, May). Smart Digital Edition Management: A Blockchain Framework for Papyrology. Proceedings of the 2024 Computers and People Research Conference. https://doi.org/10.1145/3632634.3655860
- Swindall, M. I., West, G., Brusuelas, J. H., Williams, A. C., & Wallin, J. F. (2024, March). Towards a Platform for AI-Assisted Papyrology. Past Meets Future Workshop at the 2024 International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI 2024).
- Swindall, M. I., West, G., Brusuelas, J. H., & Wallin, J. F. (2022, November). Crowdsourcing Image Datasets: An Examination of Ground-Truth in Labeling, Text Segmentation, & Sampling Bias. The Tenth AAAI Conference on Human Computation and Crowdsourcing Doctoral Consortium.
- Swindall, M., Player, T., Keener, B., Williams, A., Brusuelas, J., Nicolardi, F., D'Angelo, M., Vergara, C., McOsker, M., & Wallin, J. (2022). Dataset Augmentation in Papyrology with Generative Models: A Study of Synthetic Ancient Greek Character Images. 4948–4954.
- Swindall, M. I., Croisdale, G., Hunter, C. C., Keener, B., Williams, A. C., Brusuelas, J. H., Krevans, N., Sellew, M., Fortson, L., & Wallin, J. F. Exploring Learning Approaches for Ancient GreekCharacter Recognition with Citizen Science Data. 2021 17th International Conference on Escience (Escience), 128–137.

## **Refereed journal Articles**

West, G., Swindall, M. I., Keener, B., Player, T., Williams, A. C., Brusuelas, J. H., & Wallin, J. F. (2024). Incorporating Crowdsourced Annotator Distributions into Ensemble Modeling to Improve Classification Trustworthiness for Ancient Greek Papyri. Journal of Data Mining & Digital Humanities, Documents historiques et reconnaissance automatique de texte. https://jdmdh.episciences.org/12958

### **Invited Talks**

- Understanding Ancient Manuscripts Using Crowd-sourcing and Data Science. Matthew I. Swindall, Graham West, James H. Brusuelas, John F. Wallin. AWS Human-in-the-Loop Science Summer Seminar Series. Presented Virtually. August 17, 2023.
- Generative AI and Higher Education. John F. Wallin, Matthew I. Swindall, Isaac Shirk. Middle Tennessee State University AI Initiative Research Conference. Murfreesboro, TN. November 10, 2023.
- A.I. Assisted Papyrology: Integrating Deep Learning into the Scholarly Workflow. Matthew I. Swindall, Graham West, James H. Brusuelas, John F. Wallin. Alpha, Aleph, and AI: Languages of the Ancient Mediterranean and Near East Conference. Bristol, United Kingdom. June 14, 2023.
- Dataset Augmentation in Papyrology with Generative Models: A Study of Synthetic Ancient Greek Character Images. Matthew I. Swindall. Middle Tennessee State University Scholars Day. Murfreesboro, TN. March 22, 2022.

#### **Certifications**

• Neo4j Graph Database Certified Professional

## **Employment**

#### **Graduate Assistant**

2019 - 2024

Middle Tennessee State University

- Management of various computational projects involving Optical Character Recognition (OCR) and object detection/recognition, semantic segmentation, micro-controllers, microcomputers, electrical circuits, robotics, 3D printing, laser etching/cutting, and augmented/virtual reality.
- Design & Prototype STEM demonstrations and institutional hardware/software tools.
- Equipment training and technology coaching.
- Designed & curated numerous STEM exhibits including a Lego block sorting robot, a Bluetooth enabled LED text sign with Android app, and a real-time object detection/segmentation exhibit.

#### **Physics & Astronomy Tutor**

2015 - 2016

Middle Tennessee State University

- Tutored students in physics courses including Calculus-Based Physics 1 and 2, Electricity and Magnetism, and Classical Mechanics.
- Tutored students in astronomy courses including Introductory Astronomy, Solar System Astronomy, and Stars Galaxies and Cosmology.
- Tutored students in first year chemistry courses (Chemistry 1 and 2).
- Tutored students in advance mathematics courses including Calculus 1, 2, and 3.

Teller 3 2007 - 2013 First Tennessee Bank

- AML/BSA Compliance, Vault & ATM control and maintenance, Account Management
- Foreign Exchange, Branch auditing, Staff training
- Operated single-person satellite branch performing all banking related duties of a nearly-full-service branch.
- Won numerous awards including the FTB Presidents Award.